Tamara Paula Temple

Webologist and Software Crafts-person



Summary

Working at the intersection of Rails, GraphQL, and React, developing modern web applications with fast response times. Deeply experienced in software architecture, design, and development methodologies, especially related to the disciplines of web applications, user experience, team building, and processes.

Skills

α				1
(÷	er	ıeı	ra	л

software engineering, web development, mentoring, consulting, facilitating, teach-

ing, business analysis

engineering

Software APIs, architecture, backend, coding, debugging, frontend, full-stack, GraphQL,

REST, testing, tool chains

frameworks

Libraries + Rails, React, Vue, ApolloClient, ApolloServer, GraphQL, Sinatra

Languages Ruby, JavaScript, Python 3, Shell, CSS3, SCSS/SASS, HTML5, PHP, Perl

Tools Emacs and Org-mode, RubyMine, Webstorm, rake, Thor, make, Node.js, webpack,

babel, npm/npx, Storybook, yeoman (yo), Miro, Notion

low-level design, macro- and microservices,

Databases PostgreSQL, Redis, TimeScaleDB

Servers AWS ECS, EBS, S3, Cloudfront, Netlify,

nginx

Testing Minitest, RSpec, Jest, Testing Library

Methods

Agile development, scrum master; Continuous everything – testing, integration, deployment (CT/CI/CD); Functional Programming; Object-oriented analysis, design, programming, and testing; Precision elicitation and facilitation, communication for action; Process flow analysis, systems theory, cybernetics; Program architecture and design; NLP (Neurolinguistic Programming) practitioner; Structured analysis, design, development, and testing; Test-/behaviour-driven development; Time series analysis; User-/task-centered design

Experience

Senior Rails Engineer, Wherefour, Remote

One of three full-time engineers working mainly with Rails on the back end, adding new features.

- O Importing orders from a 3rd party
- Automating testing of a major new feature
- O Fixing some defects and small asks from customer success

2020-2022 Staff Software Engineer, Drip, LLC, Remote

Primarily focused on providing consumer and market analytics, insights, and guidance in the Drip app that enables Drip customers to become more capable email marketers. Acted as a project manager to plan, document, and track projects for the team. Software architecture and design for major features in the insights area, and providing mentoring, direction and guidance to other engineers in Drip.

- o Developed an architecture for providing recommendations, insights, and proposed next actions to Drip users (i.e. email marketers)
- O Developed a microservice to deliver time scale metrics in order to speed up customer analytics pages

- Designed an architecture to provide a Guidance System that would be able to take requirements and copy for guidance from any product team and others, and provide it to the front end where needed based on metrics and benchmarks
- Member of the Diversity, Equity, and Inclusion team at Drip, and led the DEI Affinity Groups project to produce a guide for forming and running affinity groups (i.e. employee resource groups) within Drip
- Led a team to produce a mentoring and learning environment at Drip, including a guide for mentors and mentees, tools to find or offer mentoring, connecting mentees with mentors, and reporting results
- In the absence of any project management or leadership in the insights area, acted to perform discovery, planning, discussion, documentation, and create the Epics and Stories for each project, and monitored seeing it through to completion
- 2017-2020 API-driven Rubyist, React/GraphQL Maven, ReachLocal (Gannett), Kickserv Product, Minneapolis, Minnesota/Remote

Software engineering across the entire application stack from the back end in Ruby on Rails with a PostgreSQL database, implementing a GraphQL server controller with various queries, types, mutations, and resolvers to implement a GraphQL API, and create a React front end that consumes that GraphQL API with ApolloClient in order to replace the legacy JavaScript code from over a decade of various implementation styles and libraries, giving a modern, cohesive approach to front end web application development.

- o developed the Rails GraphQL backend for the product.
- o architected and developed the JavaScript front end code in React to provide a good separation of concerns ensuring testability and writing tests where none existed prior; lowering maintenance costs, and ensuring easy replaceability to enable new features to be added with less overall effort and more predictability.
- o built Rails models, controllers, views, and React components for new Kickserv features.
- o rebuilt all the tooling for building, testing, and delivering front end code with the Rails application, using modern build technology such as webpack (using webpacker), jest, and the JavaScript Testing Library
- 2001-2017 **Independent Contractor**, *Pontiki Software Crafts*, Mendota Heights, Minnesota/Remote Contract software development of web applications, websites, and tools
 - o Clients: Ackmann and Dickenson, Software for Good, Bluewaterbrand, Novu, Shopzilla
- 1980-2001 Various positions, Hewlett-Packard (San Jose, Palo Alto, CA), Control Data (Arden Hills, MN)
 Internal Process and Technology Consultant, Senior Software Engineer/Scientist, Software Engineer
 Manager of 10 engineers, Senior Software Quality Engineer
 - o 10 years as Internal Cunsultant helping software teams level up in productivity and quality
 - \circ 3 years Senior Software Engineer developing tools for network configuration and management
 - o 2 years Software Engineering Manager with 10 software engineers
 - \circ 5 years Senior Software Quality Engineer running a networking interoperability test lab and quality engineering on a technical team producing TCP/IP

Education

1975-1980 Bachelor of Science, Computer Science, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, 3.2 GPA

Additional Training Structured analysis, design, programming and testing, System testing, Objected oriented analysis, design, programming and testing, Consulting and facilitating skills, Neurolinguistic programming certified practitioner, Project management, Public speaking and presentation skills, You Don't Know JS with Kyle Simpson, Advanced JavaScript, Numerous courses through FrontendMasters.com on React, Webpack, GraphQL, JAMstack, Angular, others